Spalding Family Papers
Spalding Family Papers
1796-1901
Spalding family.
2.0 linear ft.
Material relating to the Evans, Ellicott, and Spalding families of western New York, some of whom were Quakers. Members of these families were involved with the Holland Land Company, the Erie Canal, agriculture, and the temperance and anti-slavery movements. Correspondence (1804-1887) primarily of David E. Evans and his son, Ellicott Evans; legal and financial papers, including contracts, deeds, and wills; and 9 diary volumes (1832-1884) of Lyman A. Spalding of Lockport; photographs, and clippings.
148678
Biographical History
The Spalding, Evans and Ellicott families (some of whom were Quakers) were prominent in the early history of western New York, and various family members were involved with the Holland Land Company, the Erie Canal, agriculture, and the temperance and anti-slavery movements. Their rise coincided with a decision by the directors of the Holland Land Company to sell all lands in the so-called Holland Purchase, a vast tract between Lake Ontario and the Pennsylvania border. Pressure on the American frontier forced this decision upon Dutch investors, no less than European turmoil around 1800, when "Empires were daily swinging from their moorings" (Batavia Times, September 15, 1826). At the turn of the century, therefore, the Holland Land Company contracted with Americans to dispose of the land.
The first resident company agent was Joseph Ellicott who had served the Holland Land Company as a surveyor in Pennsylvania and New York. He was succeeded by Jacob S. Otto, who died in office in 1826. Ellicott's nephew, David E. Evans, held the post for the next ten years, and during this time he managed to parcel out more land than his two predecessors combined. Peter J. VanHall served briefly in 1837, but at this juncture the Holland Land Company's control over the remnant of the Purchase was disrupted by world depression, proprietary mismanagement, and armed debtors converging on the land office.
In the process of developing the Holland Purchase Joseph Ellicott founded Buffalo and Batavia. He also encouraged the construction of turnpikes and canals across western New York through his political influence and an offer of 100,000 acres to the Erie Canal Commission. At the end of his life of prosperity, power and bachelorhood, Ellicott divided his wealth among several brothers and sisters, three of whom had married into the Evans family.
David E. Evans, son of Rachel Ellicott and Lewis Evans, succeeded Joseph Ellicott in the management of the family fortune. He lost much of it in the panic of 1837, however. His son, Ellicott, pursued an academic career after attending Harvard. Ellicott Evans became a professor of law and political economy at Hamilton College, where he remained until the early 1880's.
The Ellicott and Evans families were united to the Spaldings of Lockport, New York, when Charles Evans, another son of David E. Evans, married Alice Jane Spalding. Her father, Lyman A. Spalding, was a significant member of the Lockport community after its foundation. By marrying Amy Pound in 1824 he combined two prominent Quaker families owning valuable property along the Erie Canal.
For further information, refer to the following family trees:
Spalding family (1)
Spalding family (2)
Brinkerhoff family
Brown family
Ellicott family
Evans family
Pound family
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Spalding Family Papers consist of correspondence, legal and financial records, journals and miscellany. While the legal and financial documents relate to the Ellicott properties, and many of the letters were written to members of the Evans family, the most significant items in the collection are the journals of Lyman A. Spalding. Genealogical charts, constructed from the Spalding Memorial (1897) and information in these papers, follow this description.
Correspondence spans the years 1804-1887, and while letters of all three families are present, the greater part revolve around the figures of David E. Evans in the early period and his son, Ellicott, in the later period. The letters are arranged chronologically and an index is provided below.
Some of the gathering political controversy between old Clintonians and new Bucktails can be detected in exchanges among Joseph Ellicott, Martin Van Buren, David E. Evans and William L. Marcy, but most of the correspondence deals with commercial and family matters.
The Lyman A. Spalding Journals, which begin in 1832, contain a wealth of observations about farming, merchandising, canal commerce, politics and reform over a period of fifty years. Passages from this continuous narrative indicate that Spalding was a sensitive diarist with a wide range of interests. He knew or saw from a distance many prominent Americans of his day -- Benjamin Lundy, Lucretia Coffin Mott, Martin VanBuren, Theodore Dwight Weld, Gerrit Smith, Horace Greeley -- and he gave all a line or a paragraph in his diary. The style is spare but artfully appropriate for the recording of everyday events in rural New York. Spalding took part in the temperance and abolition movements and is said to have operated in the underground railroad.
Legal and financial documents consist of contracts; court judgements; two indentures (1800 and 1804), one for a nine-year-old boy, the other for a seven year-old girl, both apprenticed to Erastus Spalding; memoranda (1819) about a proposed court house, jail and adjoining commons in Batavia; two copies of a formal claim against Paul Busti by Joseph Ellicott (1825) together with a legal opinion in the dispute (1822); autographed military commissions of David E. Evans by Governor Daniel D. Thompson (1812), and Charles Evans by Governor Horatio Seymour (1864); deeds, mostly for the properties of Joseph Ellicott and David E. Evans; miscellaneous receipts and vouchers; and wills, codicils and property inventories of Joseph Ellicott and his sister, Rachel Ellicott Evans.
Miscellany includes old newspapers from Batavia, Buffalo and Lockport; offprints and broadsides, biographical data; ephemera, which consist of pencil sketches, photographs, programs and verse; a lot map of Ellicott and Evans properties in Buffalo. There is also a copy of the Holland Land Company map of 1804. Newspaper clippings once laid in among the leaves of the Spalding journals have been placed in folders following the journals, while others remain firmly laid into the journals at front and rear.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and Journals are arranged chronologically. Legal and financial papers and Miscellany are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Activism and social reform; Ellicott family -- Archives.; Evans, David Ellicott, 1788-1850.; Evans, Ellicott.; Evans family -- Archives.; Spalding family -- Archives.; Spalding, Lyman A., 1800-; Holland Land Company.; New York (State) -- History.; Erie County (N.Y.); Lockport (N.Y.); Niagara County (N.Y.); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Wills.
Acquisition Information
Bulk of collection purchased, 1968.
1888 correspondence, gift of Len Chaitin, 2015.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  A selected index to the correspondence is provided at the end of this finding aid.
  - General, 1804-1882; 11 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1885-1887 (Box 1)
  - General, 1888; envelope only (Box 1)
    Gift of Len Chaitin, 2015.
  - General, undated (Box 1)
- Journals
  - Volumes I-III, 1832-1848 (Box 3)
  - Volumes IV-VI, 1848-1868 (Box 3)
  - Volumes VII-IX, 1868-1884 (Box 3)
  - Clippings from Journal VI (Box 3)
  - Clippings from Journal VII (Box 3)
  - Clippings from Journal VIII (Box 3)
- Legal & financial papers
  - Contracts & judgements, 1835-1901 (Box 2)
  - Indentures, 1800-1814 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1819-1825 (Box 2)
  - Military commissions, 1812-1864 (Box 2)
  - Real estate deeds, 1796-1835 (Box 2)
  - Receipts & vouchers, 1830-1887 (Box 2)
  - Wills, codicils and inventories, 1823-1851 (Box 2)
- Miscellany
  - Biographical data (Box 2)
  - Broadsides, 1830 (Box 2)
  - Ephemera, 1837-1880 (Box 2)
  - Fragments (Box 2)
  - Maps & plans, circa 1851 (Box 2)
  - Newspapers, 1823-1894 (Box 2)
  - Survey map of Holland Land Company tracts, 1804 (Box 3)
    "Map of Morris's Purchase or West Geneseo [and] the Boundary lines of the several Tracts of Land Purchased by the Holland Land Company.... Boundary lines of Townships...of New York and Indian Reservations: Laid down from actual Survey...by Joseph & B. Ellicott 1800. To the Holland Land Company their General Agents Theophilus Cazenove & Paul Busti Esquires This Map Is respectfully inscribed by the Authors."
  - Surveys (Box 2)
Selected index to correspondence
Adams, John C. 1844 Feb 12, Clyde, to Evans, Ellicott
Allen, Samuel 1828 Jan 31, Rochester, to Spalding, Lyman A. 1828 Mar 12, Rochester 1828 Mar 25, Rochester 1828 Jun 30, Rochester 1829 Feb 20, Albany, with "Resolutions of the Canal Commissioner, Albany, 1829 Feb 19" 1829 Mar 27, Albany 1829 May 6, Lockport 1843 Jan 26, Toledo 1844 Jan 26, Toledo
Backer, George P. 1835 Oct 22, Buffalo, to Evans, David E.
Bishop John of Nova Scotia See John, Bishop of Nova Scotia
Bleekar, H. 1835 May 26, Albany, to Evans, Ellicott
Bolles, James A. 1843 May 29, Batavia, to Evans, David E.
Bowne, Walter 1833 Dec 6, New York, to Evans, David E. 1834 Jul 16, New York
Brinkerhoff, George 1830 Nov 22, Utica, to Evans, David E.
Brinkerhoff, Lloyd 1836 Nov 19, Albany, to Evans, David E.
Brinkerhoff, Marie 1836 Apr 13, Albany, to Evans, Ellicott 1837 Nov 23, Albany 1841 Oct 4, Albany
Cony, Walter 1850 Dec 8, Buffalo, to Evans, Charles
Cooper, C.N., et al. 1839 Jan 4, Buffalo, to Evans, Ellicott
Cooper, Paul A. 1879 Aug 6, Albany, to Evans, Ellicott
Cowperthwait, Joseph 1831 Feb 7, Philadelphia, to Evans, David E.
Davis, Brooks & Co. 1850 Sep 4, New York, to Evans, Charles
Dean, Elisha 1830 Jun 7, Rochester, to Spalding, Lyman A.
Dudley, Charles E., et al. 1822 Oct 21, Albany, to Ellicott, Joseph
Eliot, Samuel 1839 Nov 4, Boston, to Evans, Ellicott
Ellicott, Ann B. 1823 Jul 15, Ellicott Mills, to Ellicott, Joseph
Ellicott, Thomas 1826 Apr 22, Baltimore, to Evans, David E.
Evans, Charles W. 1835 Sep 8, Batavia, to Evans, Ellicott 1837 Oct 4, Medina 1838 Jun 21, Geneva 1838 Dec 16, Batavia 1839 Apr 28, Batavia 1839 May 16, Batavia 1841 Mar 25, Lockport 1841 Dec 17, Lockport 1842 Mar 7, Lockport 1842 May 26, Lockport 1842 Jun 17, Lockport 1842 Jul 4, Lockport 1842 Oct 4, Lockport 1842 Oct 12, Lockport 1842 Nov 18, Lockport 1882 Jul 14, Buffalo
Evans, Charles W. 1840 Apr 13, Buffalo, to Gwinn, William R. (includes property valuation of Rachel Evans)
Evans, Charles W. 1857 Aug 21, Lockport, to Rogers, Henry W.
Evans, Charles W. 1847 Mar 25, Lockport, to Spalding, Lyman A. 1847 Apr, Lockport 1860 Mar 4, Lockport
Evans, David E. 1812 ? 1814, Fort Gray, to Ellicott, Joseph 1820 Jan 4, Albany 1820 Apr 26, Baltimore 1821 Mar 23, Albany 1822 Feb 6, Albany 1822 Feb 17, Albany 1822 Jun 30, Batavia 1822 Aug 4, Batavia
Evans, David E. circa 1865 Sep 26, Washington, to (Evans?), Charles
Evans, David E. 1825 Apr 29, Batavia, to Evans, Rachel
Evans, David E. 1823 Apr 3, Batavia, to Gwinn, Hannah
Evans, David E. 1821 Jun (draft), to Van Buren, Martin
Evans, Ellicott 1843 Nov 7, Batavia, to Evans, Charles
(Evans?), Fanny no year Sep, to (Spalding?), Kate
Evans, Henry 1838 Mar 2, Batavia, to Evans, Ellicott
Evans, Lewis 1831 Nov 5, Baltimore, to Evans, David E.
Evans, William 1825 Dec 24, Baltimore, to Evans, David E.
Flagg, A.C. 1826 Nov 23, Albany, to Evans, David E.
Ganson, John 1840 Aug 13, Canandaigua, to Evans, Ellicott 1840 Oct 30, Canandaigua 1840 Dec 5, Canandaigua 1841 Oct 2, Canandaigua 1841 Oct 4, Canandaigua
Gomels (?), Thomas G. 1865 Mar 10, Montreal, to Spalding, Amy P.
Gough, John B. 1850 Mar 13, Buffalo, to Spalding, Lyman A.
Greig, John 1820 Jan 28, Canandaigua, to Ellicott, Joseph
Gwinn, William R. 1847 Spring, to Spalding, Lyman A.
Hartwell, M.C. 1852 Jan 25, Washington, to Evans, Charles
Hartwell, M.C. no year Aug 6, St. Catharines, to (Spalding?), Kitty
Hobart, John Henry 1819 Jan 12, New York, to Evans, David E. 1822 Aug 7
Ivies, L.S. 1824 Apr 10, Philadelphia, to Evans, David E.
James, William See under Dudley, Charles E., et al.
John, bishop of Nova Scotia 1829 Jun 1, Halifax, to Evans, David E.
King, Rufus 1825 Feb 24, Washington, to Evans, David E.
Kirkland, C.M. 1836 Feb 22, Detroit, to Evans, Ellicott
Knower, B. See Dudley, Charles E., et al.
Livingstone, Edward See Marcy, William L., et al.
Loring, C.W. 1840 Apr 28, Cambridge, to Evans, Ellicott
Luden, H.J. DeBie 1839 Feb 5, Amsterdam, to Evans, David E.
Ludin, Samuel L. 1842 Jul 1, Rochester, to Evans, Charles
Magee, John 1826 Aug 22, Bath, to Evans, David E.
Marcy, William L. 1824 Aug 10, Albany, to Evans, David E. 1830 May 24, Albany
Marcy, William L., et al. 1825 Sep 23, Albany, to Evans,David E.
Marcy William L. 1827 Aug 7, Albany, to Spalding, Lyman A.
Mason, John Y. 1845 Apr 11, Washington, to Evans, David E.
Montross, P.A. 1830 Jul 29, at sea, to Spalding, Lyman A.
Muncy, Ann 1847 Jun 29, Hillhouse, to Muncy, James 1848 May 17, Aberdeen
Nova Scotia, John, bishop of See John, bishop of Nova Scotia
Pompelly, Marie 1849 Feb 24, to Evans, Ellicott
Porter, Peter Buell 1835 Feb 17, Blackrock, to Evans, David E.
Pound, Amy See Spalding, Amy Pound
Pruyn, John V.L. 1863 Nov 24, New York, to Evans, Charles 1864 Jun 15, Washington
Seaver, William A. 1837 Dec 5, Batavia, to Evans, Ellicott 1837 Dec 21, Batavia 1838 Feb 12, Batavia 1838 Feb 25, Batavia 1838 Apr 9, Batavia 1838 Apr 26, Batavia 1838 Apr 30, Batavia 1838 May 1, Batavia 1838 Jun 12, Batavia 1838 Sep 17, Batavia 1838 Sep 19, Batavia 1838 Oct 16, Batavia 1838 Nov 13, Batavia 1839 Jan 3, Batavia 1839 Mar 23, Batavia 1839 Apr 30, Batavia 1839 Jun 29, Batavia 1842 Mar 16, Batavia
Seymour, Henry, Jr. See Cooper, C.N., et al.
Skinner, Roger See Dudley, Charles E., et al.
Smith, David 1840 Jan 31, Batavia, to Evans, Ellicott 1841 Mar 24, Batavia 1841 Mar 31, Batavia 1841 Jul 21, Batavia 1842 Sep 26, Portland, Maine, to Evans, Ellicott 1845 Jan 28, New York 1853 Sep 13, New York
Spalding, Amy Pound 1823 Jan 21, Perrington, to Spalding, Lyman A. 1823 Jul 16, Perrington 1832 Jun 17, Avon 1838 Apr 8, Lockport 1845 Dec 17, Lockport
(Spalding?), Edna 1885 May 6, to (Evans?) Alice (Spalding) includes a folk remedy for tapeworms
Spalding, Erastus 1820 Jul 27, to Spalding, Lyman A. 1830 Jul 6, Saratoga Springs
Spalding, Lyman A. 1860 Dec 6, Albany, to Spalding, Amy P. 1861 Jan 18, Albany
Spalding, Lyman A. 1825 Oct 27, to Spalding, Erastus
Spalding, L. Austin 1887 Sep 22, Aix-la-Chapelle, to Evans, Spalding
Spalding, L. Austin 1861 Mar 22, Washington, to Evans, Charles
Spalding, L. Austin 1864 Aug 12, Washington, to Spalding, Lyman A. 1865 Feb 26, New York
Spencer, Ambrose 1804 Feb 28, Albany, to Ellicott, Joseph 1807 May 7
Spencer, Ambrose 1819 Mar 23, Albany, to Evans, David E.
Spencer, J.C. 1842 May 9, Washington, to Evans, David E.
Stevens, Kenneth P. See Cooper, C.N., et al.
Swift, (General) 1832 Aug 7, Geneva, to Evans, David E.
Talcott, Samuel A. 1821 May 10, Albany, to Evans, David E.
Thompkin, Daniel D. 1814 Mar 7, Albany, to Ellicott, Joseph
Throop, E. 1819 Mar 17, Auburn, to Evans, David E. 1829 Jun 18, Auburn 1830 Jan 24, Albany 1832 Dec 8, Auburn
Van Antwerp, Cornelius See Marcy, William L., et al.
Van Buren, Martin See under Charles E., et al.
Vanderkemp, John J. 1837 Feb 9, New York, to Evans, David E.
Vanderkemp, John J. 1840 Dec 26, Philadelphia, to Smith, Junius A.
Van Dyck (?), C.A. 1862 Nov 6, New York, to Evans, C.
Verplanck, Isaac D. 1835 Sep 2, Batavia, to Evans, Ellicott 1835 Dec 8, Batavia
Wadsworth, James 1835 Jun 25, Geneseo, to Brimmer, Martin
White, Jonas 1835 Oct 6, Stuyvesant, to Van Buren, Martin
Williams, George, Jr. 1840 Feb 12, Baltimore, to Evans, Ellicott
Williams, J. 1830 Aug 2, Saratoga Springs, to Spalding, Lyman A.
W--(?), Norton & Co. 1869 Jan 25, London, to Hale, Henry